<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of fasting, and of Lent, and of the antiquitie, dignitie, and great necessitie thereof preached vpon the 14. of Februarie, anno 1607 at Shaftesbury / by Io. Mayo.</title>
            <author>Mayo, John K.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22438968</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22438968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of fasting, and of Lent, and of the antiquitie, dignitie, and great necessitie thereof preached vpon the 14. of Februarie, anno 1607 at Shaftesbury / by Io. Mayo.</title>
                  <author>Mayo, John K.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Hall, for John Helme, and are to bee sold at his shop, in S. Dunstones Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸ E².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXIX, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Lenten sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25535:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF <hi>faſting, and of Lent, and</hi> of the antiquitie, dignitie, <hi>and great neceſsitie thereof;</hi> Preached vpon the 14. of <hi>Februarie, anno 1607.</hi> at <hi>Shaftesbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By IO. MAYO.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Daniel 9. 3.</bibl>
               <p>And I turned my face vnto the Lord GOD, and ſought by Praier and Supplications, with faſting, and ſackecloth, and aſhes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>W. Hall,</hi> for <hi>John Helme,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop, in S. Dunſtones Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25535:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull <hi>WILLIAM WILKS Doctor</hi> in Diuinitie, and one of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Chaplaines in ordinarie:</hi> And to the Worſhipfull <hi>Maior and Recorder of the Borough</hi> of Shafiesbury; and to the Maſters and Burgeſſes of <hi>the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was neuer any age that bragged more of knowledge, and yet, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any that had leſſe ſoundnes. For as the harts of men were neuer more empty, and their hands neuer more idle: ſo their tongues were neuer more ſtirring, and their braines neuer more ſtuffed: not ſo much ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying to doe what they know, as to find what they may beleeue: being like to thoſe <hi>Pyrro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Philoſophers or <hi>Scepticks</hi> of whom <hi>A.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25535:3"/>
               <hi>Gellius</hi> writeth Lib. 11. Cap. 5. who would alwaies ſeeke and conſider, but neuer decree, appoint, nor comprehend any thing; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to their owne fantaſie, and the depth of their owne capacity. Some thinke, that Gods ſchoole is more of vnderſtanding than affection; and they endeuour to haue much knowledge though it bee without zeale, and to get much skill, though it bee without loyallobedience and good gouernment. It is not ſufficient for ſuch to bee of Gods court, but they will be of his counſell alſo. They will needs prie into his Arke; inquire into things not reueled; and be puffed vp, and be wiſe in themſelues; teaching, preaching, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading that, which tendeth rather to liberty, fancy, and ſelfe-will, than to praier, faſting, almes and mortification of the fleſh. Yea, and not content with that, they depraue and traduce others that follow not their owne humors and opinions therein; and ſpeake of them, not humbly as <hi>Judah</hi> ſaid of an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gen. 38. 10. <hi>She is more righteous than 1: but hatefully and without peace, as</hi> Ioſephs <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did of him.</hi> Gen. 37. 4.</p>
            <p>The reaſon and occaſion why and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I write this, may ſoone bee vnderſtood, both of you, who are a teacher in the Church, and haue had great experience of this cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and encroaching euill: and of you alſo, who beare publike office and authority in the common-wealth, hauing ſeene the pangs and practiſes of theſe kind of people, ſtill murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and muttering againſt princely procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb facs="tcp:25535:3"/>
in eccleaſticall gouernment, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt things in themſelues indifferent, but by authority neceſſary, as commanded by his Maieſty. It is charities precept to ſpeake well of all; and Ciuilities rule not to backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the abſent. And yet we ſee, that ſome of them conſider of other mens doings, that tend to forme, order and decencie, As Satan con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of <hi>Iob,</hi> and his actions, when God ſaid vnto him; <hi>Haſt thou conſidered my ſeruant Iob?</hi> And he ſignified yea, but it was to belie &amp; calumniate him. And although we now ſee the ſtaffe of our bread broken, and the euill arrowes of death and famine ſent amongſt vs, to make vs humble our ſelues before the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of heauen, with faſting, praier, and repentance: yet they can not be brought to obſerue and keepe any time and ſeaſon of abſtinence and faſting, commanded by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but they will rather hazard an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the peace of the church, and to the good of their cuntrey, than ſuffer their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites to be bridled, and their zeale to be guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the limits of any good lawes.</p>
            <p>The conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this matter hath moued mee to publiſh this Sermon, and to dedicate it, both to you, whom for many cauſes I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect &amp; reuerence, &amp; whoſe fauour and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I haue found in no ſmall meaſure; and to al you alſo, who haue ſhewed your loue and countenance towards me, not only in hearing patiently, but in conſtruing courteouſly, that which is now come to the generall view of others. Accept of it I pray, and take it as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:25535:4"/>
from him, who wiſheth you all increaſe of happineſſe, and all grace mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and peace in Chriſt IESVS.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Shaftesbury <date>the 28. of Nouember. 1609</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Worſhips moſt aſſured <hi>to be commanded</hi>
IO. MAYO,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25535:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 69. 10.</bibl>
               <q>I wept, and chaſtened my ſelfe with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and that was turned to my reproofe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE booke of the Pſalmes is a booke <hi>Sapientall:</hi> ſet foorth vnto vs by the holy Ghoſt, and doth ſerue for manie and diuers purpoſes. Someof the Pſalms ſerue formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, as we may know by their ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. Some for Praiers, ſome for Thankſgiuing, ſome for Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſome for Doctrine, ſome for Prophecie, &amp; ſome for Storie. All to this end and purpoſe, to giue vnto vs preſent remedies againſt troubles and temptations of the mind and conſcience, and to make vs liue in the true faith, feare and loue of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25535:5"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iſhai,</hi> a man according to Gods owne heart, was called the ſweet Pſalmiſt of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who not onely made Pſalmes himſelfe, but ordained wiſe and ſkilfull men to make Pſalmes, and to prophecie with all kind of inſtruments, as <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and his ſonnes: <hi>Corah,</hi> &amp; his ſons: <hi>Heman,</hi> and his ſonnes: <hi>Ieduthan,</hi> and his ſonnes. Which Pſalmes, or prayſes according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, were chiefly ordained to praiſe God, &amp; to giue him thanks for his bleſſings and benefits; and are called the Pſalmes or the ſongs of <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe the moſt part of them were made by him.</p>
            <p>This Pſalme, in which my text is contained, was made by <hi>Dauid,</hi> and is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a wiſhing ſong or Pſalme:</hi> and of <hi>Apollinarius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ſong of a conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heart;</hi> &amp; it doeth containe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially two parts: Firſt, a Petition from the 1. verſe to the 30. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, a praiſe-full concluſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 30. verſe to the end of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25535:5"/>
Pſalme. For the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> being atype of Chriſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, doeth ſéeme to haue written this Pſalme in the name of Chriſt and of his Church, euen as the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall hiſtorie doeth ſhew it; &amp; as the Apoſtles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues do apply it.</p>
            <p>Theſe words which I haue read vnto you being written in the 10. verſe, doe containe in them two parts, 1. An Aaction of <hi>Dauid. 2.</hi> A conſtruction of that Action by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. An action of <hi>Dauid,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of his Paſſion &amp; Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Of his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in theſe words, <hi>I wept.</hi> Of his mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in theſe words, <hi>And chaſtened my ſelfe with faſting.</hi> The conſtruction of the Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in theſe words; <hi>And this was turned to my reproofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wept</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid).</hi> He wept not heere as he did for <hi>Abner,</hi> or as hee did for the death of his ſonne <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> He wept not here as hee did when he fled from his ſonne <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> or as hee did for the death of his ſonne <hi>Abſolon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Hee wept not heere as <hi>Iacob</hi> did for his ſonne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25535:6"/>
               <hi>Ioſep,</hi> or as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did when hee heard he ſhould die; but hee wept here as <hi>Peter</hi> did when he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied his maſter, and as <hi>Joſiah</hi> did when he heard the words of the booke of the Law. Hee wept with care, with compunction, and with contrition of heart, for his ſinnes and offences committed againſt the Lord, euen as hee did in Pſalm. 6. 6. where he ſaith: <hi>Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie night waſh I my bed, and water my couch with my teares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wept,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> being a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, a Prince, and the ſeruant of the Lord. A thing not vnfitting, nor vnſeemely for a Prophet, a Prince, &amp; the ſeruant of the Lord in ſuch a caſe. Becauſe ſuch kind of waeping is a ſigne of true and heartie repentance; It is the fruit of paſſion, a token of a broken heart, and (as <hi>S. Baſill</hi> ſaith,) <hi>the food of the ſoule.</hi> And therefore the Lord himſelfe ſaith by his Prophet <hi>Ioel 2. 12. Turne vnto me</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>with all your heart, and with Faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25535:6"/>
ſaith <hi>Luke 6. 21. Bleſſed are yee that now weepe, for ye ſhall laugh.</hi> And the Apoſtle S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked rich men, Chap. 5. 1. <hi>Goe to now, ye rich men, weepe and howle for your miſeries that ſhall come vpon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And chaſtened my ſelfe with faſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Inſome tranſlations, <hi>I wept, &amp; my ſoule faſted:</hi> as it is in Pſal. 35. 13. <hi>Leuit. 23. 27.</hi> And as <hi>Apollinarius</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Pſalme ſaith:</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>I haue broken or ſubdued my ſoule with the labours or ſweates of faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propher <hi>Dauid</hi> not onely wept, and ſhewed his paſſion, but chaſtened himſelfe with faſting, &amp; ſhewed his Mortification. So did the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as he himſelfe writeth, <hi>1. Cor. 9. 27. But I doe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and beate downe this my bodie, and bring it into ſubiection: why? Leſt when I haue Preached to others, I my ſelfe ſhould be reproued.</hi> So did the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> as wee may read, <hi>Cha. 10. 3.</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>I was in heauineſſe for three weeks of daies. I ate no pleaſant bread, neither came fleſh nor wine into my mouth.</hi> So did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25535:7"/>
that bleſſed <hi>Hilarion,</hi> as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> writeth in his life, who would ſay vnto his bodie, thus, as S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> there relateth: <hi>Ego (Aſine) faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am te vt non calcitres. O thou Aſſe,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Hilarion</hi> to his bodie) <hi>I will make thee that thou kicke not. I will feed thee, not with barlie, but with chaff. J will tyre thee with hunger, J will load thee with great thriſt, I will bring thee ouer heats &amp; coldes, that thou ſhalt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke vpon thy meate than wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherewith did the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> chaſten himſelf? with faſting. <hi>I wept, and chaſtened my ſelfe with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi> So he did in Pſalme 109. 23. where he ſaith: <hi>My knees are weake through faſting, &amp; my fleſh is dried vp for lacke of fatneſſe.</hi> So did the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the houſe of the Lord. Judg. 20. 26. So did Anna the daughter of <hi>Phanuel</hi> in the Temple of the Lord. Luke 2. 37. So <hi>Dauid</hi> and his men wept and faſted till euen, for <hi>Saul</hi> and for <hi>Ionathan</hi> his ſonne, for the people of the Lord, and for the houſe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25535:7"/>
becauſe they were ſlaine with the ſword, 2. Sam. 1. 12. And ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe faſted, praied, and lay all night vpon the earth for the childs life. 2. Samuel 12. 16.</p>
            <p>Some thinke that abſtinence and faſting are one and the ſame, becauſe they are both imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame matter, and manie times the one is taken for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſome thinke that to faſt, is nothing elſe but to liue ſoberly and conueniently to nature. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence euen as temperance, doth bind euery man to keepe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it. For as it is not ſit for any man at any time to liue intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, ſo it is not meet for any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to admit that which is againſt true abſtinence, becauſe we ought to eate and drinke no more than reaſon willeth, or neceſſitie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture requireth.</p>
            <p>Faſting doeth not bind all, nor alwayes, but ſome onely in their time and place. For moſt certaine it is that our Sauiour Chriſt and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25535:8"/>
his Apoſtles, with many others both before and after them liued ſoberlie and conueniently to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet they not alwayes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. For if they had alwayes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, our Sauiour Chriſt would neuer haue ſaid: <hi>The bridegroome</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 3. 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall bee taken away from them, and then ſhall they faſt in thoſe dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that was turned to my reproofe,</hi> Here is the <hi>Conſtruction. Dauid</hi> was reproued for his wéeping, and for chaſtening himſelfe with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. By whom? By his enemies, who would deſtroy him guiltleſſe, and were mightie. Pſal. 69. 4. By his enemies, who ſpake againſt him, teſted vpon him, and being drunke, made ſongs vpon him. It hath not alwayes bene a fault, but a faſhion for wicked men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue and reprehend vertue &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in good men. And therefore <hi>Iudas</hi> grudged at <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> for breaking of the bore of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for powring it on Jeſus head Mark. 14. 4. The Phariſees
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25535:8"/>
reproued Chriſts Diſciples to his face for plucking the eares of Corne vpon the Sabbaoth day, Matth. 12, 1. And our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe was mocked, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at, ſcorned, ſcandalized, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched, reproued and reuiled by the Jewes, by the Scribes, and others, and told that he was a friend to Publicanes and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and that hee had in him <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub</hi> the prince of the Deuils. Marke 3. 22.</p>
            <p>In the time of the heathen, the Cynicke <hi>Diogenes</hi> deſpiſed all things: the Philoſopher <hi>Democritus</hi> laughed at all things: the Philoſopher <hi>Heraclitus</hi> wept at all things: the Philoſopher <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> thought hee knew all things: and the carping god <hi>Momus</hi> blamed and reprooued all things. Enuie and reproofe doe alwaies waite at vertues elbow. For <hi>Isboſeth</hi> ſhall neuer want a man in his owne campe, <hi>Elah</hi> a ſeruant in his owne houſe, and <hi>Dauid</hi> a ſonne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25535:9"/>
from his owne loines, beſides <hi>Achitophels, Doegs,</hi> and <hi>Shimees,</hi> not onely to reproue him &amp; reprehend him, but to worke treaſon and treacherie againſt him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Orator ſaith well in his firſt <hi>
                  <hi>Paradoxe,</hi> Iſta omnia talia videmus: <hi>We ſee all ſuch things, that alſo wicked men haue wealth, and do hurt the good.</hi>
               </hi> And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith truly, Pſalm. 11. 2. <hi>The vngodly bend their bowe, and make readie their arrowes within their quiuer, that they may pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily ſhoote at them which are true of heart.</hi> Thus much of the Phraſe. The Matter, as I ſaid before, is an Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Dauid</hi> conſiſting of his Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and his Mortification: &amp; a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruction of that Action by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. In the Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I haue thoght good to obſerue theſe fiue parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What Faſting is.</item>
               <item>2. How manie ſorts of Faſting there are.</item>
               <item>3. The effects of Faſting.</item>
               <item>4. The cauſes of faſting.</item>
               <item>5. The antiquitie, dignitie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie of Faſting.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25535:9"/>In the Conſtruction of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I haue thought good to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue three Particulars, and two Queſtions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The 1. Particular, what Lent is.</item>
               <item>2. By whom it was firſt ordained.</item>
               <item>3. To what end and purpoſe it was ordained.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The 1. Queſtion; <hi>Whether ſet daies, and times of abſtinence and faſting, ought to bee commaunded by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Queſtion: <hi>Whether it bee a ſinne wilfully to breake and to deſpiſe ſet dayes and times of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and faſting commaunded by authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faſting (as ſome define it) is a proper acte of Abſtinence, or a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine peculiar manner of Auſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. As other ſome define it, <hi>It is a Parſimonie of liuing, and an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence of meates. Tertullian</hi> ſaith: <hi>That it is a worke of reuerence towards God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregorie lib 5. Moral.</hi> ſaith: <hi>That it is, <hi>Quando quis pro amore Dei, &amp;c.</hi> When any one for the loue of God and</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25535:10"/>
               <hi>his owne health doeth abſtaine, not onely from things vnlawfull, but from things lawfull and graunted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That reuerend Biſhop <hi>Iewel</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> of famous memory, ſaith: <hi>That it is a religious worke ordained to teſtifie our humilitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to make the fleſh the more obedient to the Spirit, that wee may bee the quicker to Praier and to all good works.</hi> A late excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and exquiſite Diuine of ours, ſaith: <hi>That it is an helpe and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perkins Reform. Cathol. pag. 222.</note> 
               <hi>to the worſhip of God, &amp; a good worke if it be vſed in a good manner. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is a worke allowed of God, and highly to be eſteemed of all his people and his ſeruants.</hi> The Greckes will haue it to be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of not eating, or of eating nothing at all. And the Latines will haue it to bee called <hi>Ieiunium, ab inteſtino ieiuno,</hi> becauſe with hunger the bowels are voyd and empty.</p>
            <p>In the holy Scripture wee find 4 ſorts of faſts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A miraculous faſt.</item>
               <item>2. A faſt from euill works.</item>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:25535:10"/>
               <item>3. A penitenciall faſt.</item>
               <item>4. A faſt from ſurfetting,</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> and our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe vſed the Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous faſt; for they faſted 40. dayes and forty nights.</p>
            <p>Of the faſt from Euil works, the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> writeth, Chap. 58. 5. <hi>Nunquid eſt tale ieiunium quod elegi, &amp;c. <hi>Js it ſuch a faſt that I haue choſen, that a man ſhould afflict his ſoule for a day, and to bow downe his head? &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Penitentiall</hi> faſt, wee read in the third Chapter of <hi>Ionas,</hi> the ſeuenth verſe: where the king of the <hi>Niniuites</hi> at the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ionas</hi> proclaimed a faſt in theſe words, <hi>Let neither man nor beaſt, bullocke nor ſheepe taſte any thing, neither feede nor drinke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the faſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Surfetting, our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Luke 21. 34. <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to your ſeiues, leſt at any time your hearts bee oppreſſed with ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drunkenneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:25535:11"/>Some there bee that make two ſorts of faſts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>A Publike faſt.</item>
               <item>And a Priuate faſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A Publike faſt, is that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and vſed according to the Preſcription of law, the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the ſuperiour, and the Cuſtome of the countrey.</p>
            <p>A Priuate faſt, is that which is done voluntarily without any conſtraint or compulſion of the Law.</p>
            <p>Some there bee, that make 4. ſorts of faſts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. a Moſaicall faſt.</item>
               <item>2. An Euangelicall or Eccleſiaſtical faſt.</item>
               <item>3. A couetous faſt.</item>
               <item>4. A Philoſophers faſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Some there be that make 4. other ſorts of faſts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Spirituall faſt from ſinne.</item>
               <item>2. A corporall faſt from eating and drinking.</item>
               <item>3. A faſt of neceſsitie.</item>
               <item>4. A Chriſtian and Religious faſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of the Spirituali faſt from ſinne,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25535:11"/>
we doe read in the 7. Chap. of the Prophet <hi>Zacharie,</hi> the 5. 6. 7. verſes.</p>
            <p>A Corporall faſt from eating and drinking, is of 3. ſorts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Naturall.</item>
               <item>2. Super-naturall.</item>
               <item>3. Ciuill or Politike.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Naturall is that, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Phyſicke, for healths ſake.</p>
            <p>Super-naturall, is as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of Saul, which <hi>Ionathan</hi> was angry with, becauſe the people waxed faint.</p>
            <p>Ciuill or politike, is that which is for the generall good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the whole Common weale.</p>
            <p>A faſt of Neceſſite, is that which we cannot auoid, as in the time of dearth. That great Schooleman <hi>Aquinas</hi> doth call this faſt, <hi>Ieiunium ieiunij, <hi>a faſt, of a faſt:</hi>
               </hi> becauſe the earth forbeareth her fruits, we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare food, and would eate, if wee had it.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtian or Religious faſt, is either <hi>Common, or ordinarie; Speciall, or extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25535:12"/>Some there be that make ſeuen ſorts of faſts, which be theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Pharaſaicall faſt.</item>
               <item>2. A gluttonous faſt.</item>
               <item>3. A deceitfull faſt.</item>
               <item>4. An inordinate faſt.</item>
               <item>5. A ſuperſtitious faſt.</item>
               <item>6. An hereticall faſt.</item>
               <item>and 7. a diueliſh or ſatanicall faſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>A Pharaſaicall faſt,</hi> is to faſt with hypocriſie and diſſimulation, to get an applauſe and opinion of holineſſe among the people, of which Chriſt himſelfe ſpeaketh in Matth. 6. 16. <hi>Moreouer when you faſt, looke not ſowre as the hypocrites, for they disfigure their faces, that they might ſeeme vnto men to faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Gluttonous faſt,</hi> is not to keepe the lawes of due temperance in faſting. Of which S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth in his <hi>2. lib.</hi> againſt <hi>Iouinian:</hi> where ſome (ſaith hee) which were to faſt, the Dinner or Supper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they began their faſt, would eate ſo much that they were not well able to digeſt it in two dayes after.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:25535:12"/>
               <hi>A Deceitfull faſt</hi> is to vſe wine, or any other meate or drinke before or after meales, <hi>vt fallamus ieiunium,</hi> that wee may deceaue or coſen our faſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Inordinate faſt,</hi> is to keepe no order of Chriſtian charitie and wiſedome, but to paſſe ouer the meane of reaſon, as well in kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it, as in leauing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Superſtitious faſt,</hi> is to apply ones ſelfe rather to the manners of the Jewes, the Saracens &amp; the Mahumetans, then of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; or to thinke one ſelfe not well to haue faſted, if one breake his faſt before the ſtarres appeare in the night. Or to faſt in dayes exempt from faſting by the lawes and cuſtome of this Land, not with any good or godly cauſe, but with contempt and diſdaine of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Hereticall faſt,</hi> is to faſt with the cuſtome and minde of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichêes, Nouatians, &amp; other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes; or doubtfully to obſerue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25535:13"/>
times which they out of a certaine error haue conſecrated to faſting.</p>
            <p>A diueliſh, a ſatanicall faſt, is to obey the law of faſting, and yet to make no end of ſinning, but to continue and perſeuere in the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cuſtome and delight thereof.</p>
            <p>A rare and renowmed Diuine of ours, whoſe iudgement is beſt to be followed in this matter, doth make thrée ſorts of faſtings:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Morall.</item>
               <item>2. A Ciuill.</item>
               <item>3. A Religious faſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Morall faſting, is the practiſe of ſobrietie and temperance: when as in the vſe of meates &amp; drinkes, the appetite is ſo reſtrained, that it doeth not exceed moderation.</p>
            <p>Ciuill faſting, is when vpon ſome particular and politike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, men abſtaine from certaine meates. As in this our common weale, the lawe doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne vs to abſtaine from fleſh meate in this time of Lent, vpon Fridayes and Saterdayes, and other times of the yéere.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:25535:13"/>A Religious faſt is, when the dueties of Religion are practiſed in faſting; as the exerciſe of Praier and humiliation.</p>
            <p>The effects of Faſting, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeciall for our ſelues, or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall for the whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale. Speciall for our ſelues; to bridle the wantonneſſe of the fleſh, and to make it the quicker to Praier, and to all good workes. General for the whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, to preſerue the brêed of cattle, to maintaine the Princes nauie, and the Calling of the Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erman.</p>
            <p>And the like is affirmed by our moderne Diuines, that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and right ends of faſting are thrée.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To make the mind the more attentiue in the meditation of the dueties of godlineſſe to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the rebellion of the fleſh may bee ſubdued: For the fleſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being pampered, becomes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of all, and all licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25535:14"/>3. To profeſſe our guiltineſſe, and to teſtifie our humilation before GOD, for our ſinnes and offences committed againſt him.</p>
            <p>This is proued by many places of Scripture, as Numb. 30. 14. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay 5. 11. Rom. 14. 21. where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith: <hi>Non eſt bonum, <hi>It is not good, neither to eat fleſh nor drinke wine, whereby thy brother ſtumbleth or is offended.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is proued by many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Scripture, as of <hi>Dauid, Daniel, Tobias, Cornelius, Paul,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>This is proued by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ancient fathers, and eſpecially theſe: of that learned father Saint <hi>Auſtin, lib. 3. Chap. 5.</hi> againſt <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> where hee ſaith: <hi>Non ideo carnes prohibentur quia malae ſunt, ſed quia illarum epulae carnis lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uriam gignunt. <hi>Fleſh is not therefore</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Ser. 66. ſup. Cant.</note> 
               <hi>forbidden becauſe it is ill, but becauſe the banquetting thereof breedeth riot.</hi> Of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who ſaith: <hi>Abſtineo à carnibus, &amp;c. <hi>I doe abſtaine from</hi>
               </hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25535:14"/>
               <hi>fleſh, leſt whiles I doe too much nouriſh the fleſh, I doe alſo nouriſh the vices of the fleſh.</hi> And of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> in his ſeuenth Homilie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the latter end of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, where hee ſaith: <hi>Abſtinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia propter hoc recepta eſt. <hi>Abſtinence is for this cauſe receiued, that it may bridle the wantonneſſe and riot of the fleſh.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cauſes of faſting are many, and ſpecially 4.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>2. The Commandement of God.</item>
               <item>3. Faith.</item>
               <item>4. Repentance.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt is the cauſe, for three reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe by Nature wee are giuen to gluttony and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which naturall vices wee doe not leaue without the grace of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:25535:15"/>2. Becauſe it is not ſufficent to abſtaine from gluttony and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, vnleſſe the heart doeth alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent thereunto. 3 Becauſe Faſting is a good worke, and all good workes are the fruits of the holy Ghoſt. Gal. 5. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Commandement of God,</hi> is the cauſe, for 2. reaſons. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is expreſſed in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Lord, that wee ſhould abſtaine from gluttony and drunkenneſſe. 2. Becauſe the Lord by his commandement doth require of vs ſuch Abſtinence, and forbids the contrary.</p>
            <p>Faith is the cauſe; becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it can not bee well done, nor acceptable vnto the Lord. For whatſoeuer is without faith, is ſinne: and without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance</hi> is the cauſe: becauſe faſting is a true ſigne thereof, and an outward meanes whereby wee doe acknowledge our guiltineſſe and vnworthineſſe of the leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Almightie God. And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25535:15"/>
therefore the faſting of the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites</hi> was a ſigne of their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and their repentance a ſigne and fruite of their faith, whereby they beleeued the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Ionas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much what faſting is: How many ſorts of faſtings there are: Of the Effects of faſting: and the Cauſes of faſting. Now of the Antiquitie, Dignitie &amp; Neceſſitie of faſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faſting</hi> is no new inuention, nor any late vpſtart. The Antiquitie of it doeth make it venerable; and the Perpetuitie of it vntil this day doeth highly grace it. Some haue deriued it from Paradiſe, &amp; made it as auncient as the firſt man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> For the forbidding of the tree of knowledge of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, they ſay was a law of Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence.</p>
            <p>The Stories of Gentilitie and Poetry, doe ſhewe the Antiquitie of faſting moſt plainely. For <hi>Ceres</hi> had her faſt, <hi>Iupiter</hi> his faſt, and <hi>Priamus</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> bewailes the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25535:16"/>
death of his ſonne <hi>Hector</hi> with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and in duſt. Beſides, the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> vſed it, the Prophets for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke it not, and our Sauiour Chriſt and his Diſciples departed not from it.</p>
            <p>The Dignitie of faſting is great, eminent, and very excellent: for it is the exerciſe of nature, theprac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Gentilitie, &amp; the Law and the Goſpel of Chriſt himſelfe. It is comfortable, Diuine, Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, Spirituall, wholeſome, and an inſtrument to euerie good work. It doeth adminiſter wiſedome, it doeth extinguiſh the wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh, doeth lift vp the mind to heauen, it doth vnit man with God, and as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayth, <hi>It doeth caſt out deuils.</hi> Nay our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe ſo ſayth, as wee may read in Matth. 17. 21. where it is ſaid; <hi>This kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils is not caſt out but by Faſting and Praier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to ſee what the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers haue written of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25535:16"/>
&amp; how much they haue attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted thereunto. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. de Virg.</note> 
               <hi>That it is the meate of the Angels, and that hee who doeth vſe it, is to bee thought of Angelicall order: Great</hi> (ſayth hée) <hi>is the force of Faſting. Great things and excellent things are done by it. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith thereof thus: <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunium</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Ser. 1. de Ieiu.</note> 
               <hi>Prophetas ingenerat, &amp;c. <hi>Faſting doeth breed Prophets, and doeth adde ſtrength to the mightie. In warres it doeth adde fortitude: in peace, it doeth teach quietneſſe.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may ſpeake in a word, as many holy Fathers as haue béene, thou ſhalt finde them all to bee directed and guided to leade a life worthy of God, by abſtinence and faſting. <hi>Iſydorus</hi> ſayth of it thus: <hi>Eſt res ſancta, opus coeleſte, &amp;c. <hi>It is an holy thing, an heauenly worke, a gate of the kingdome, a forme of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to come: and hee that doeth it well and holily, is alienated from the world, is made ſpirituall, and is ioyned to God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25535:17"/>The Neceſſitie of faſting is ſuch and ſo great, that in this our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, ſet dayes and times of Abſtinence and faſting, are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for ciuill and politike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; and (as I ſaid before) to maintaine the Princes Nauy, to preſerue the breed of Cattell, and the calling of the Fiſherman.</p>
            <p>Of this, I will ſay euen as a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Religious Diuine of ours ſaith in the concluſion of the 12. point of Faſting: <hi>It were</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to bee wiſhed, that faſting were more vſed of all Chriſtians, in all places: conſidering the Lord doeth daily giue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perkins Refor. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. pag. 231.</note> 
               <hi>vs new and ſpeciall occaſions of publike and priuate faſting.</hi> Theſe words of our Diuine we find to be true: for the All-great, and Euer-gratious GOD of Heauen, hath of late giuen vnto vs new and ſpeciall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of both priuate and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike faſting.</p>
            <p>You know, how after the death and diſſolution of our late Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of happy memory <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> wee all feared great tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25535:17"/>
and tumults to ariſe amongſt vs: And yet we ſaw that our peace and proſperitie was not eclipſed, by reaſon of our good and godly King, whom the louing Lord of Heauen hath placed vpon the ſeat of this kingdome, to rule his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a wiſe and prudent heart.</p>
            <p>You know, how the Almightie Lord hath ſhaken the ſword of the deuouring Angell manie yeeres together vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and vpon moſt cities, townes, and villages of this Land, to rowſe vs vp (if it might be) from the ſleepe of ſinne and ſecuritie, and to make vs humble our ſelues vnto him with faſting, prayer and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. You know how mightily and miraculouſly the ſame Lord hath deliuered vs out of the very iawes of death and deſtruction; and from a treaſon, What treaſon? A treaſon of ſuch horror and monſtrous nature, that the tongue of man neuer deliuered the like, the eare of man neuer heard the like, the heart of man
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25535:18"/>
neuer conceited the like, and the malice of any earthly and infernall deuill neuer practiſed the like.</p>
            <p>And you know alſo, how this great Lord hath made the ſeas &amp; the waters but this laſt yeere to rage and to rore vpon this Land, with vnheard &amp; vnſéen flowings, inundations and riſings, to the drowning of Corne and Cattle, Men, women and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea, and of whole Pariſhes. If now wee doe not conuert from our wicked waies, and giue our ſelues to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, praier and amendement of our liues, ſurely, ſurely, ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, yet iuſt iudgements, yea, ſome great and grieuous plagues and puniſhments are like to come vpon vs; which God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, Chriſt for his merits ſake, and the Holy Ghoſt for his Names ſake, withdrawe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and keepe from vs. Thus much of the fiue Particulars ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the Action. Now of the three Particulars and the 2. Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s obſerued in the <hi>Conſtruction.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:25535:18"/>
What Lent is. The name of Lent was not at firſt idely giuen, nor without great reaſon &amp; graue conſideration. For it doeth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a time of forty daies, according to the Greeke and Latine denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Men in ancient times haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced this number of 40. with ſo great obſeruation, that they ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated a feaſt thereof which they called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a feaſt of forty daies.</hi> This number of fortie hath not lightly bêen neglected, nor lewdly, nor looſely beene reiected, becauſe it was thought a myſticall and wholeſome number, and verie ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant in the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of expiation, penitencie &amp; great myſteries. For forty daies and forty nights the<note place="margin">Gen. 7. 4.</note> raine was vpon the earth. After forty daies the waters ceaſed, and<note place="margin">Gen. 8. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Noe</hi> opened the windowes of the Ark which he had made. <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the mount, how long? 40. daies<note place="margin">Exod. 24. 18.</note> and 40. nights. The deſtruction of the <hi>Niniuites</hi> was deferred, how long? till after forty daies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:25535:19"/>The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had 40. man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the wilderneſſe. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were 40. yeeres in the wilderneſſe, and before the time of that myſticall number was out, they could not enter into the land of promiſe. <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> and Chriſt<note place="margin">Of this number ſee, Gen. 6. 3. and 18. 29.</note> himſelfe faſted 40. dayes and forty nights. Our Sauiour Chriſt was forty weekes in the wombe of the bleſſed Virgin. Forty dayes from<note place="margin">Numb. 18. 34. &amp; 33. 38 &amp; 13. 26.</note> his Natiuity he remained in <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem,</hi> becauſe he was offred in the Temple. Forty moneths hee<note place="margin">Leuit. 12 4</note> preached publikely. Forty houres he lay in his Sepulchre, and the fortieth day after his Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he aſcended into Heauen.</p>
            <p>Al which, ſome Diuines in times paſt haue written not to bee done without the ſecret myſterie and proprietie of this number. Alſo, this number of forty, is a number of affliction and repentance, and therefore the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſlept fortie dayes vpon his right ſide for the tribe of <hi>Juda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Auſten</hi> doeth call the time of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25535:19"/>
Lent, <hi>tempus venerabile, <hi>a venerable</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 4. 6. Ser. in Sab. ante Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drag.</note> 
               <hi>time. S. Bernard</hi> doeth call it, <hi>tempus Christianae militiae, <hi>A time of a Chriſtian warfare. Gratian</hi>
               </hi> and others of the<note place="margin">Ser. 1. de Quadrag. Part 3. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 5. fol. 579.</note> ancient fathers doe call it, <hi>Decima dierum,</hi> the tenth of the dayes; <hi>Or the imitation of Gods conuerſation:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in it wee doe pay vnto God the tenths of the yeare.</p>
            <p>Some of the ancient fathers haue gone ſo farre, that they haue thought Lent not to be an humane inſtitution, but a diuine and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall tradition, and firſt broght into the Church by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle <hi>Peter.</hi> Where as likely &amp; ſomewhat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable it is, that the firſt Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Lent was by <hi>Teleſphorus,</hi> the 6. Pope in <hi>Rome,</hi> as ſome doe rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon him, a thouſand foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and three ſcore yeares ſince and more. For this <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> firſt<note place="margin">Platyna in vit. Teleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phori.</note> ordained that full ſeuen weekes before Eaſter all Clarkes ſhould faſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſh, becauſe (as they then thought) there ought to be a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in faſting, euen as the life of the Clergie ought to bee differing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25535:20"/>
from the life of the Laitie, which time was called <hi>Quinquageſima,</hi> as <hi>Gratian</hi> writeth, <hi>1. part. diſtinct. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This time of Lent in ancient times hath beene diuerſly begun, diuerſly obſerued, and about it there haue beene diuers tontenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and controuerſies. The Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Church beganne their Lent on <hi>Quinquageſima.</hi> Other ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne it on <hi>Sexageſima,</hi> as in the time of <hi>Bede.</hi> Some other on <hi>Quadrageſima,</hi> as <hi>Mediolanum,</hi> &amp; all Greece. Some vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Aſhe-wenſday,</hi> and ſome vpon an other time.</p>
            <p>This time, in times paſt alſo hath bin diuerſly obſerued. Some in this time haue abſtained from all things which had life in them, as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> did. Some haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten onely birds. Some haue eaten onely fiſhes. Some haue abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from egges and all kinde of fleſh meate; And ſome haue eaten nothing but dry meate, as <hi>Socrates</hi> doeth write, <hi>lib. 9. Chap. 38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There haue beene alſo diuers contentions and controuerſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the continuance of this time
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25535:20"/>
how long it ſhould be faſted: when ſome would faſt but one day, ſome two daies, ſome a weeke, ſome 2. weeks, ſome more, &amp; ſome 40. daies as <hi>Ierenaeus</hi> writeth, <hi>lib. 5. Chap. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By reaſon of theſe differences and diuerſities about this time of Lent, and becauſe this time was firſt ordained and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet is ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obſerued therein: ſome there be that count this time a time of ſuperſtition, &amp; would haue no Lent at all, ſcorning in very lawfull pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies to be imitators of the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; and like ſelf-witted Captaines diſdaining to vſe any ſtratageme vſed before of the enemy, althogh the putting of it in exploit might giue them aſſured victory.</p>
            <p>To ſuch kind of people, that may well and truely be ſaid, which our Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie ſpake at the conference at <hi>Hampton Court. No Church</hi> (ſaid his Maieſty) <hi>ought farther to ſeparate it ſelf from the Church of Rome, either in doctrine, or in ceremony, then ſhe hath departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſelf, when ſhe was in her flouriſhing</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:25535:21"/>
Or that which reuerend <hi>Hooker</hi> doeth write in his <hi>5. lib.</hi> of <hi>Eccleſi. Poll. It is not our beſt pollicie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for the eſtabliſhment of ſound Religion, in all things to haue no agreement with the Church of Rome, although vnſound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The end and purpoſe why and wherefore Lent was firſt ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was, not onely to preſerue the breede of Cattell, to maintaine the Princes Nauie, and the Calling of the Fiſherman, but eſpecially for the worthy receiuing of the bleſſed Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or Lords Supper. For in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the primatiue Church, many came to the holy myſteries promiſcuouſly without any prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Which when the ancient fathers vnderſtood, and ſaw the great harme and hurt that did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe of that negligent comming to that holy Table, they eſtabliſhed a Preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; decreed forty dayes of faſting, praying, hearing of the Word of God, and comming to the Church: that in thoſe dayes the people being dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25535:21"/>
purged by praier, by faſting, by reares, by compaſſion, and by other ſuch meanes, they might come to theſe holy myſteries with purer conſciences and better deuotion.</p>
            <p>The time of Lent was ordained at this time of the yeere, in the Spring time, for three reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By reaſon of heate encreaſing, and abundance of humors or moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture growing or comming on.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To preſerue brêed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: becauſe at this time there is a generall bréed and encreaſe of all things,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe of the feaſt of the Lords Reſurrection, which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a peculiar Preparation. For the general receiuing of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> or Lords Supper, did alwaies fall out in the ſpring time.</p>
            <p>I might ſpeake more and much of theſe Particulars, but I will conclude them with the ſaying of a worthy &amp; praiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> worthie Knight in a booke which he writeth of the relation of the religion of the weſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25535:22"/>
parts of the world, where he ſaith thus: <hi>I am ſo far off</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from thinking the inſtutition of Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, or the reſtraint in it vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that I rather encline to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Greeke Church, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their great Lent, haue three other Lents alſo in the yeere, though the other neither ſo long, nor in them ſo ſtrict an obſeruation.</hi> Thus much of the 3. Particulars. Now of the two Queſtions. The firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether ſet daies and times of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and faſting ought to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faſtings are either of mens own frée &amp; voluntary accord, as their particular deuotion doeth mooue them thereunto; or els they are publikely enioyned in the Church, and required at the hands of all men, <hi>Montanus</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth) was the firſt author of theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times of faſting, &amp; of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of this ſet lawe-making of faſting. For which cauſe manie there bee that reiect and renounce the ſame. But moſt certaine and aſſured it is, that ſet daies and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25535:22"/>
times of faſting appointed in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall conſiderations to bee kept of Chriſtian people, tooke not their beginning either from <hi>Montanus,</hi> or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other whoſe hereſies may preiudice the credit &amp; due eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, but haue their ground in the law of nature; are allowable in Gods ſight, were in all ages heeretofore vſed, and may till the worlds end be obſerued, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſingular vſe and benefit.</p>
            <p>They haue their ground in the law of nature, becauſe they teach vs to kéepe order and moderation, ſobrietie and temperance in our meates and drinkes. For nature doeth content her ſelfe with a litle. Nature is our beſt guide, which if we follow, we ſhal neuer go aſtray. And therefore <hi>Cyneas</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher was of this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that when the gods framed Nature, they went beyond their owne ſkil, why? becauſe the maker (quoth hee) is ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing made. They are allowable in Gods ſight, becauſe they are daies partly of pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and ſorrow, and partly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25535:23"/>
a ſigne of duety, deuotion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence towards God.</p>
            <p>They were in all ages héereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſed for preuention of diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and riot, for the preſeruation of Cattell, and the maintenance of Sea-faring men, becauſe the decay of the one, and the waſte of the other, could not well bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented without ſuch politike order and conſideration.</p>
            <p>They may till the worlds end be obſeruéd not without ſingular vſe &amp; benefit, becauſe they draw men to penitency, to temperance, to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, to all Chriſtian duety and deuotion, and to the generall good, and publike profit of the whole Common-weale.</p>
            <p>Some there bre that would proue ſet dayes and times of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence and faſting out of the Scripture, and ſpecially out of theſe places; <hi>Leuit. 16. 29. The tenth day of the ſeuenth moneth, ye ſhal hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſoules. Leuit. 23. 27. The tenth day of this ſeuenth moneth, ſhal be a day of reconciliation.</hi> And <hi>Zach. 7. 5.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:25535:23"/>
               <hi>When yee faſted and mourned in the 5. and 7. moneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Trueth it is, that theſe ſet and preſcribed faſts in <hi>Leuiticus</hi> were commanded of God, as a part of a legall worſhip, which had their end in the death of Chriſt. And trueth it is alſo that the faſts ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> were appointed vpon occaſion of the preſent afflictions of the Church in <hi>Babilon,</hi> which ceaſed vpon their deliuerance. But our ſet dayes and times of Abſtinence and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting are appointed and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be obſerued, not for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or religions ſake, but for Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Politike regards; and not for the priuate good, but for the generall good of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale. Which if they were left to the peoples owne choiſe, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and will, it may ſoone bee coniectured what would follow thereof: becauſe the corruption of the time is ſuch, and the wickednes of mans nature is ſo exorbitant, that it is a hard matter to hold the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25535:24"/>
ordinarie ſort of people within the liſts of duetie, obedience, and good order, without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the ſuperiour, and the ſeueritie of good lawes. For which cauſe very neceſſary it is, yea a good and godly thing it is, that ſet daies &amp; times of abſtinence and faſting ſhould be appointed and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by authoritie. Which no one will diſlike or diſdaine, vnleſſe hee bee like vnto Aerius, who oppoſed himſelfe againſt faſting, and ſaid: <hi>Theſe ſet faſts away with them, they are</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephipha. haer. 75.</note> 
               <hi>Iewiſh, and bring men vnder the yoke of ſeruitude. If I will faſt, let me chuſe my time to faſt, that Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be not abridged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might proſecute this Queſtion more at large, but I hope euerie charitable Chriſtian, and equally-minded man and woman is heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſatiſfied. And therefore I will conclude it with this argument or this ſyllogiſme.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Whatſoeuer is for the general good and publike profit of the whole Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25535:24"/>
that ought to bee appointed and commanded by authoritie:</item>
               <item>But ſet dayes and times of Abſtinence and faſting are for the generall good and publike profit of the whole Common-weale.</item>
               <item>Therefore they ought to bee appointed and commanded by authoritie.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The other Queſtion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Whether it be a ſinne wilfully to breake and to deſpiſe ſet daies and times of Abſtinence and faſting commanded by Authoritie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>To hold this queſtion affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely, may peraduenture ſeeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome a <hi>Paradox,</hi> or rather a groſſe errour and grieuous abſurdity. But ſeeing Kings and Princes are Chriſts deputies here on earth to gouerne the world, and in the Scripture are called gods: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt willed his diſciples to beware of offences; and ſeeing S. <hi>Paul</hi> willed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Corinthians</hi> to giue no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25535:25"/>
offence neither to the Jewes, nor to the Grecians, nor to the Church of God; I can not chuſe but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and ſay, that it is a ſinne wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and without cauſe to breake and deſpiſe ſet dayes and times of Abſtinence and faſting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by Authorite; and this ſhall bee proued vnto you by 6. ſpeciall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By the fift Commandement.</item>
                  <item>2. By the teſtimony of S. Paul. Rom. 13. 1.</item>
                  <item>3. By the definition of Sinne.</item>
                  <item>4. By Examples,</item>
                  <item>5. By the Ancient Fathers.</item>
                  <item>6. By generall Councels.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This is proued by the fift Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. In the 5. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which is the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the ſecond Table, we are commanded to honour our Parents: where, by honour is meant, loue, feare, and obedience; and by our Parents not onely our naturall Parents, but all Kings, Princes, Gouernours, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours which doe rule vs. Well
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25535:25"/>
then, if we wilfully breake and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe ſet dayes and times of Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and faſting commaunded by Authoritie, we doe not honour our Superiors. If wee doe not honour our Superiors, we breake this Commaundement. If wee breake this Commandement, I hope none will deny but we ſinne.</p>
               <p>This is proued by the teſtimony of S. <hi>Paul, Rom. 13. 1.</hi> where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith: <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher power.</hi> Why? becauſe there is no power but of God. We muſt not (ſaith he) reſiſt the power: for if we reſiſt the power, we reſiſt the ordinance of God. They that reſiſt, what ſhall they receiue? They ſhall receiue to themſelues iudgement. Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence I frame this argument. <hi>Whoſoeuer doeth reſiſt the power, doth reſiſt the ordinance of God. But they that wilfullie breake and deſpiſe ſet daies and times of abſtinence and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting commanded by Authoritie, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the power. Therefore they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the ordinance of God.</hi> If therein
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25535:26"/>
they doe reſiſt the ordinance of God, who can deny but that they ſinne?</p>
               <p>This is proued by the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne. To ſinne, as <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſaith, is <hi>facere quod non licet, <hi>to do that which is not lawfull to doe.</hi>
                  </hi> Héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence I drawe this argument: <hi>Whoſoeuer doe that which is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, doe ſinne: but they which wilfully breake and deſpiſe ſet daies and times of Abſtinence and faſting commanded by Authoritie, doe that which is not lawfull; therefore they doe ſinne:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is proued by Examples. <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> of the Lord not to eate of the tree of knowledge of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: If hee did, hee ſhould die the death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aarons</hi> ſonnes were commanded<note place="margin">Leuit. 10. 9</note> of the Lord, not to drinke wine, nor ſtrong drinke in their miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: which commandement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they brake, they were ſlaine. The man of God, that came out<note place="margin">1. Reg. 13.</note> of Iuda was ſlaine by a Lion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25535:26"/>
being ſeduced by the falſe Prophet, hee did eate bread, and dranke water in his houſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Lords Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> would haue put his ſonne<note place="margin">1 Sam, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionathan</hi> to death, becauſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly he tooke a little honny con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his commandement. If <hi>Adam, Aarons</hi> ſonnes, and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> of God were puniſhed of the Lord for their not abſtinence: and if <hi>Ionathan</hi> was in ſo great danger, for breaking his fathers comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in eating a little honny: Is it not a ſinne before God for vs, wilfully to breake and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ſet daies and times of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, and faſting commanded by Authoritie, ſeeing wee are commanded of the Lord to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues to our Princes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; and bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence truely and vnfeinedly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them?</p>
               <p>Let vs yet goe further.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25535:27"/>
The noble kings <hi>Ezekias, Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> and <hi>Ioſias,</hi> made lawes for the exerciſe and the recalling of Gods ſeruice. That Chriſtian and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Emperor <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made lawes alſo in things pertaining to holineſſe towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Church. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his ſucceſſour, tooke the ſame courſe. King <hi>Alured</hi> or <hi>Alfred</hi> appointed and commanded ſet daies and times of Abſtinence and faſting. And ſo did king <hi>Edgar, Anno Dom. 958.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had it beene a ſinne for people in thoſe daies to haue broken theſe their Princes lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, wilfully, wantonly, and without cauſe? and ſhall we thinke that it is not a ſinne for vs in theſe daies to doe the like?</p>
               <p>This is proued by the teſtimony of the ancient fathers. Moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and aſſured it is that <hi>Auſten, Ambroſe,</hi> and other of the ancient fathers were of this mind, and thought it a ſinne wilfully to break and to deſpiſe ſet daies and times
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25535:27"/>
of Abſtinence and faſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Authoritie. <hi>S. Auſten</hi>
                  <note place="margin">de temp. Ser. 62.</note> calleth them new teachers that ſhut out the merite of faſting, and aſketh what ſaluation we can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine if we blot not out our ſinnes by faſting, ſéeing (ſaith hee) the Scripture ſaith, <hi>that faſting and almeſdeeds doeth deliuer from ſinne, <hi>Alijs diebus ieiunare</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith he) <hi>reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium est aut praemium, &amp;c. <hi>To faſt on other daies is a remedie or reward: but not to faſt in Lent is a ſinne. S. Ambr. in ſer. 25. de Quadrag.</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other things, <hi>Non leue eſt peccatum. <hi>Jt is no ſmall ſinne to breake a faſt that is commanded.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although theſe two ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had their errors, and in ſome ſort thought corruptly of faſting: yet I will ſay of them and of their opinion concerning faſting; as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib. 5.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. pol. lib. 5. pag. 208.</note> 
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt. Poliicie. Concerning euery mans duety herein</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which</hi> Auſten and Ambroſe <hi>are alleadged to haue done, is ſuch, that all men fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring equitie muſt needs allow, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:25535:28"/>
                  <hi>it alſo if they affect peace.</hi> Well then, if according to maſter <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> iudgement al men muſt néeds allow this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if they fauour equitie and affect peace: then I hope I may ſay, that it is a ſinne wilfully and without cauſe to breake and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ſet daies and times of Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and faſting commanded by Authoritie.</p>
               <p>This is prooued by generall Councels, and ſpecially by that of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> held in the yeere of our Lord 454. to confound the errour of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> who held, that in Chriſt, God and Man make but one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>The Councell of <hi>Mentz</hi> vnder<note place="margin">Canon 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the great, made this decrêe. <hi>Si quis indictum ieiunium ſuper biendo contempſerit, &amp;c. <hi>If any one ſhall with pride contemne faſting commanded, and will not obſerue it with other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, let him be accurſed.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like was eſtabliſhed by the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> in their 63.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25535:28"/>
Canon, By the Councell of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicen</hi> in their 50. Canon, and by the Councell of <hi>Toletan</hi> in their 7. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
               <p>If thoſe Councels thought them fit to bee accurſed and excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, that would not obſerue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting commanded by Authoritie; ſhall not wee thinke, that they thought it a ſinne in them that did wilfully breake and deſpiſe the ſame?</p>
               <p>I might ſtand longer, and much longer vpon this queſtion, but I will conclude it with the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter,</hi> &amp; ſay vnto you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the Jewes, 1. Epiſt. 2. 13, and 14. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues to all manner of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome peraduenture may ſay, you haue ſpoken nothing of <hi>Imber</hi> Faſts, and Faſts on Saints Eues. What can you ſay of them? are not they altogether i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſuperſtitious, and to bee abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:25535:29"/>I pray you giue mee leaue and I wil ſpeake ſomewhat of them alſo. And 1. I will ſhew you why they were ſo called. 2. By whom they were firſt ordained. And 3. the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion why they were ordained.</p>
               <p>They were called <hi>Imber-daies</hi> vpon no other reaſon and occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of eating bread baked vnder <hi>Imbers</hi> or aſhes. Whoſoeuer doth ſay otherwiſe, ſaies it either of malice or ignorance. For the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vpon thoſe dayes vſed to faſt, and to eate nothing but bread ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnder <hi>Imbers.</hi> Which they did for two cauſes. Firſt, to pay vnto God at ſuch times, the tithes of their ſoules &amp; bodies, in thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for the fruites of the earth, and the fruites of his grace. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that the holy Ghoſt might the more plenteouſly bee powred downe vpon them which receiue holy orders. For the Sunday af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe <hi>Imber-faſts,</hi> and at no time els, alwaies hath beene, and yet ſtill is the ordering of miniſters by the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:25535:29"/>Some refer the firſt inſtitution of theſe <hi>Imber-faſts</hi> to Pope <hi>Vrbanus</hi> Some to <hi>Calixtus</hi> the 2. And ſome ſay, that they were firſt confirmed in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of <hi>Mentz,</hi> held vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the great, of which I ſpake but now, for this intent, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vpon thoſe daies ſhould come to the Church, ſhould faſt to the 9. houre, and abſtaine from fleſh and all things els.</p>
               <p>But moſt certaine it is, that theſe <hi>Imber-faſts</hi> are moſt ancient, haue béene moſt common, and in all the Chriſtian world moſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly obſerued foure times of the yeere: and therefore they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ieiunia quatuor temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the faſts of the foure times, becauſe of the foure ſpeciall turnings of the ſun, the firſt about the Spring <hi>Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall,</hi> the ſecond about the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Solſtice,</hi> the third about the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall</hi> in Autumne, and the 4. about the winter <hi>Solſtice.</hi> And vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe three daies of the wêeke, the Wenſdaies, the Fridaies, and the Saterdaies: becauſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25535:30"/>
Chriſt was ſolde vpon a Wenſday, crucified vpon a Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, died vpon a Saterday, and reſted in his ſepulcher. Theſe reaſons haue beene alleadged heeretofore for the inſtitution and obſeruation of theſe <hi>Jmber-faſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eues of Saints-daies are called in Latine <hi>Vigiliae,</hi> which is, watchings; becauſe in the time of the Apoſtles, and alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time after, watchings, prayers, and almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeds, were accuſtomed to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to faſtings. Theſe faſts on ſaints eues were not at firſt idely inuented, and haue not in times paſt beene fondly nor fooliſhly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. And they haue beene ſet (as maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> writeth, as v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers<note place="margin">Eccle. Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. 5. pag. 214.</note> of feſtiuall daies for preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſorders as much as might be: which may bee kept not without great good to the kéepers, and ſingular vſe and benefite to the whole Common-weale.</p>
               <p>Concerning which, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Corinthes,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:25535:30"/>
ſo ſay I vnto you: <hi>Let all things bee done honeſtly and according to order.</hi> Great is the dignitie of <hi>order,</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let all things.</hi> Great is the neceſſity of <hi>order:</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let all things be done.</hi> Great is the eminency and the excellency of <hi>order;</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle concludeth his Chapter with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Will you haue common dutie kept which Nature requireth? then <hi>let all things be done honeſtly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to order.</hi> Will you haue common law regarded which Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie willeth? then <hi>let all things bee done honeſtly and according to order.</hi> Will you kéepe your goods, your houſes and all things that you haue, in peace, quietneſſe and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie? then <hi>let all things bee done honeſtly, and according to order.</hi> Will you be faithfull and firme, louing and loyall ſubiects to our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne? then <hi>let all things bee done honeſtly, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:25535:31"/>And will you haue all things to go well with you, and to proſper well with you in this world: then <hi>let all things be done honeſtly, and according to order.</hi> Without this order, there is no duety, no deuotion, no chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, no concord, no law, no loue, no peace, plentie nor proſperitie, no grace, goodneſſe, nor any godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, although we heare neuer ſo much, know neuer ſo much, talke, debate and diſpute of diuinitie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much. Thus much of the<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 16</note> matter: Now of the application and the vſes.</p>
               <p>Becauſe all Scripture is giuen by inſpiration, &amp; is profitable (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> telleth vs) to teach, to improue, to correct, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſſe; we ought heere to follow the example of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and to chaſten our ſelues with faſting as he did, although by ſome it bee turned to our reproofe. Of which his faſting, <hi>Humiliation</hi> was the cauſe, euen as diuine ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the cauſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo long faſting in the Mount.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:25535:31"/>For in the holy Scriptures wee reade how not only Kings faſted, as <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets faſted, as <hi>Moſes, Elias</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel:</hi> women faſted, as <hi>Anna, Heſter, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> and <hi>Sara Raguels</hi> daughter: the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> faſted, the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Gabiſh Gilead</hi> faſted: the Apoſtles faſted: Saints, Fathers and Confeſſors faſted: yea, the very heathen (as wee reade) fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as <hi>Iupiters</hi> prieſts in <hi>Create;</hi> with the greateſt Philoſophers <hi>Antiſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Pythagoras,</hi> and <hi>Socrates.</hi> But in theſe our daies it is ſtrange to ſee, the ſcorne and the ſcandall, the contempt and the diſdaine which many make of faſting: in ſo much that if a man or a woman doeth but for ciuill and politike reſpects obſerue and kéepe ſet daies and times of Abſtinence and faſting commanded by Authoritie, he ſhall be of ſome reproched and reproued for it, &amp; he ſhall be of ſome thought to bee popiſh and ſuperſtitious. We are all now growen to exceſſe and to extreamities, to luſt, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25535:32"/>
and licentiouſneſſe. We are all for the moſt part giuen to glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie and gourmandice, to ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſenſualitie, and ſurfetting. We are all now growen to bee Epicures, to be Sibarites, and to loue the two daughters of the horſe-leach, although they ſucke out all the blood of our bodies.</p>
               <p>The beſt feaſtmaker, is thought with ſome to be the beſt Chriſtian, and the leaſt faſter, is thought with ſome not to bee the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour. Wee care not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the breed of Cattell, the maintenance of the Kings Maieſties Nauie, or the Calling of the Fiſherman. Wee care not for any good Lawes or Statutes whatſoeuer, that enioine vs to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtmence and faſting, but like <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus,</hi> we will be our own heires, and make an end of all things our ſelues: like the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they were without Kings, we will doe that which is good in our owne eies: and like the two
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25535:32"/>
ſonnes of <hi>Aaron, Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> we will offer ſtrange fire, although we be burned in the flames there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Worſhipfull, and beloued in the Lord, Men, brethren and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I pray you giue me leaue to ſay thus much vnto you: The wiſeſt and the worthieſt men of this Land are perſwaded, that the not Abſtinence, faſting, and meane diet, is the occaſion of ſo many great, grieuous, and outragious ſinnes which are committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. There was neuer more teaching, more preaching, more lawes and more Statutes, and yet neuer more exceſſe, more intemperance, more riot, more ſurferting, more hypocriſie and diſſimulation, &amp; neuer worſe and worſer liuing. The world is bold to ſurfet, and hath taken an habite to fry in words, but to fréeſe in deeds; &amp; to bee rather a diſputant than an agent in Religion, and to count ſinnes, no ſins, but to turne them from ſinnes, to trades and occupations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:25535:33"/>The world doeth bluſh, and doeth ſcorne to faſt, becauſe it thinkes it to be an abridgement of Chriſtian libertie, to bee Jewiſh, a Montani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and rather the bewraying of a diſeaſe then the exerciſing of a vertue. And therefore ſome ſay as they did in the 2. Chap. of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: <hi>Come, let vs enioy the pleaſures which are preſent, and let vs cheerefully vſe the creatures as in youth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some ſay as they did of whom the Poet writeth: <hi>Wee are a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat. ad Lollium epiſtol. lib. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and we are borne to conſume, and eat fruites, and fill our bellies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some againe will faſt, but when? when they liſt themſelues, and not otherwiſe. For when we faſt, they will feaſt: and when we feaſt, then they will faſt; And out of Lent they will eat fleſh meate, though not vpon other daies, yet vpon Fridaies and Saterdaies; and in the time of Lent, they will eate fleſh-meate ſeuen daies in the weeke: behauing themſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much like vnto them, to whom it was ſayd by our Sauiour Chriſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25535:33"/>
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <hi>We haue piped to you, and yee</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 19</note> 
                  <hi>haue not danced: we haue mourned to you, and yee haue not wept.</hi> Some againe will kéepe extraordinary faſts; but how? without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and authoritie of the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, to preuent his decree, and controle his gouernment. To ſuch kind of perſons, that may wel and truely bee ſaid which a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned Doctor hath written: <hi>A wilfull law-breaker, would</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vnion. ſect. 19. fol. 62.</note> 
                  <hi>willingly breake the law-giuer:</hi> that is, he that is not a friend and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer to the Princes lawes, can not be a friend and welwiller to the Prince himſelfe. Many good and wholeſome lawes and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes haue beene made and enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bridle the luſt and libertie of people in this point, as in the 5. and 13. yeere of our late Queene <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> and in the firſt yeere of our now gratious dread Soueraign King <hi>IAMES;</hi> which Acte, becauſe it ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned this matter, and is fit and neceſſary to be heard, knowen and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25535:34"/>
vnderſtood of all heere preſent, I wil read vnto you as it is ſet down in the booke.</p>
               <p>You which are now in place and authoritie, looke to this good Act, and to the due execution thereof, as you ought to doe. Firſt you your ſelues, giue good examples thereof in your houſes, to your children, to your ſeruants, and in other places alſo where you come, Look to thoſe Butchers, and that without all fauour or partialitie, that ſhall offend heerein, and to thoſe Tauerners, Inne-keepers &amp; Ale-houſe-keepers, which make a common courſe and cuſtome of offending heerein, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any feare or intermiſſion.</p>
               <p>You which are Parents, giue good examples thereof to your children: and all you which are maſters, miſtreſſes, and dames of houſes and families, giue good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples thereof to your ſeruants, to your apprentiſes, and to others that are with you.</p>
               <p>Let the ſuperior ſort giue good
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25535:34"/>
examples thereof to the inferiour, the richer to the poorer, and the elder to the yonger, without the honny of hypocriſie, or the leauen of maliciouſneſſe, contempt or wilfulneſſe; that wee may all liue in the feare, die in the fauour, reſt in the peace, riſe in the power, and remaine at laſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie with Jeſus Chriſt our Sauiour, to whom, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
